welcome to meditating with john varvakey
we do this every weekday morning at 9
30 a.m eastern time
with mondays alternating between a new
lesson called dharma day
and a review of the whole ecology of
practices called rupaya day
for previous lessons and sits see the
description if you're joining us for the
first time
you're most welcome but i recommend you
go to those links and immediately do
lesson one
and then every week do one or two more
lessons
and then you'll very quickly integrate
with the rest of the group
i would ask everybody to help me to
reach as many people as possible by
please liking this
video stream at the end of every session
there is a q
a please limit the questions at that
time uh
to anything from the whole ecology if
your question doesn't get answered on
the day you pose it
don't worry we gather them together we
create a storehouse and we try and work
our way through them
um if you have more encompassing
questions
uh we have a live stream general q a
every third friday of the month at 3 p.m
eastern i believe yeah
that's august the 21st uh for this month
and i think that's all i need to do
oh so i'll remind you that i'll review
uh adding
we added the arms in yesterday to the
walking to create full-blown uh brush
keys
i'll review that again uh for you
tomorrow
i think that's everything oh a reminder
one final reminder
we're going to be starting the wisdom of
of hypatia
uh on our drama day this coming monday
this coming monday
okay that's everything i i think we need
to get ready so please get yourself in
position
uh set your phones on uh do not disturb
and we will as always we'll start with
some chanting and then we'll go into
silent set
and we will begin together when i say
begin
oh
[Music]
one
oh
[Music]
one
oh
[Music]
one
all
[Music]
one
oh
[Music]
begin your silence it
communicate perhaps by reciting the five
promises to yourself
okay we have time for a couple of
questions
one is from dimitar and it begins with
an observation
uh i encourage everybody to share
observations
and comments and events that have
happened
that have been significant to them we're
trying to edify
each other as much as possible dimitar
puts the observation on the question i
noticed a while ago that i'm most calm
during basic capacity when my breath
becomes like a mirror of my mental state
and that and at the same time the
sensations themselves are vivid
i find that i can renew my interest in
my breath for a longer period if i can
sense the ongoing story of my mental
state being reflected from it
however i wouldn't say it's entirely
fused together with the sensation
it does seem more like a projection is
this something i should expect
is there something else i could aim
towards once i'm in this state
that's a very good question so
it sounds to me like
you are
what the that story is sort of the
unfolding
uh of it um that it's a lens for you
you're still aware of the lens
um so it's translucent to you rather
than just transparent to you
but you're using it as a way to more
uh more interesting yourself
with your sensations it doesn't sound
like um it's a problem uh
everything has an aspect of projection
to it
um because participation is made up of a
projection
introjection uh loop right uh
you know go to the pine uh to to learn
about pines
right the famous i think it's from basho
um so the the problem with projection is
if we're not aware of it
and it's and it's also distorted but if
you're aware you're doing it
and it's affording you becoming more
interested and involved think about
involved as the revolution
right evolving revolving evolving right
with the unfolding
of the pattern of your sensations
if it's affording you getting into
something like an absorbed flow state
um then i think you should keep doing it
dimitar i mean
um it's when we get
interested in the story for its own sake
explaining it justifying it how it
leaves with our autobiography
how it reinforces self self
referentiality
when it starts to imprison us in
that kind of locked in egocentrism
that's when it becomes problematic
um and dangerous um so
sounds to me if i'm understanding you
correctly and of course this is always a
challenge
it's always a challenge it sounds to me
like this
is fundamentally working for you um and
i've given you a few cautions a thing
of things to note for when it's not
going right and
the ways you need to frame it so that it
stays
a healthy upaya a healthy skilled
practice for you
aiden c asks a question how would you
recommend integrating union dream work
and memory techniques together with this
ecology of practices so
uh the union dream work we're going to
talk about
in the the wisdom of hypatia so when we
get
to the neoplatonism um part of the
course and we're actually doing what's
called theorja
i will take you through i'm going to
recommend a book
george slater's book of bringing dreams
to life a couple small books and we will
work through together
how to do that and you can see how to
integrate it together
for those of you who work for for those
of you for whom it works
one way of integrating mindfulness and
dreamwork together is to try to
cultivate lucid dreaming
as i mentioned before in the past this
i've had lucid dreams
um and a couple of them were sort of
profound for me
but as a regular practice this hasn't
gelled for me yet i'm going to come back
and work on it
so i won't have too much to say about
that because of lack of
significant experience or expertise but
will definitely
dreamwork law i have a lot of experience
with um so we'll be able to
um i'll show you how to integrate that
in um
memory techniques i'm not quite sure
what that means to you
uh we're going to be talking about
maximization
which is the use of maxims and other
what's called prochyron this is from
stoicism making things ready to hand
uh and those are memorization techniques
we'll talk about
that in stoicism so i think both of your
concerns
will be addressed as we work our way
through wisdom of hypatia
the memory stuff most probably in
stoicism and the dream stuff most
probably
yeah when we get to neoplatonism but
we're not starting there
on monday we're going to start with
epicureanism because that's where you
should start
you start in the world of the senses the
world of pleasure and beauty
because that is where we start in an
important way and we should never
ever leave that behind epicureanism is
not what it means today it's not about
having party and fun
it's about learning learning to savor
your the the beauties and the
the pleasures not just physical
pleasures mental pleasures
um in or as a way of encouraging
as a way of creating courage within us
epicureanism
is directed towards most essentially
overcoming fear through deep friendship
and that's what we're going to start
pursuing on monday
so thank you all for joining i want to
thank my dear friend and technomage
ammar
and my beloved son jason who is
apprenticing i guess he's a techno major
in training now
he's doing lots of work behind the
scenes uh with amar
and so that builds in some very needed
redundancy it also liberates amara to do
more have more participation and so i'm
thanking jason for all of that
please subscribe to this channel to be
notified of the next video
um you'll also find on the channel links
to
the lecture series awakening from the
meaning crisis
um the via logo series voices with
raviki
there's a new series that's going to be
coming out shortly that i'm doing with
greg
enriquez called untying the world knock
of consciousness the heart
problems of mind and meaning we've
already
i'm filming another episode with him
today and that's going to be coming out
shortly
there's a lot in the work of course
after socrates whenever
kovit will let me get to the filming
that will that's that's uh
that's that's definitely something i put
a lot of work into so there's a lot
there
a lot that can be of value to you uh
please
subscribe to me on twitter if you're not
opposed to that
for philosophical or psychological
reasons because that way and give you
uh updates about all of these streams
and all of the things
that are happening invite others who
might benefit by to
by joining this series please join the
discord server
to chat with others there's a link in
the description
a lot of the practices from the western
wisdom tradition are more about
in your life as opposed to in a sitting
there'll be things we do
together in sittings but they're more in
the life and in dialogue with others so
i'm going to be relying on
the discord server as a place to home uh
some of these new uh
some of these new practices and so i
encourage you all to
familiarize yourself with that and
become more aware of that community
and contribute to its growth like
everything that's growing
you know it needs guidance it needs
correction
it needs participation um and it needs
involvement
we do this every weekday morning at 9 30
eastern time
and i think that's all i need to say
regarding announcements
so please remember that continuity of
practice is more important than quantity
of practice
don't hold yourself to some harsh
perfectionism
hold yourself to the standard of
virtuous friendship
please remember therefore there's no
enemy worse than your own mind body
there's no friend no ally no true
companion down the path
better than your own mind and body i'll
see you all again
tomorrow take good care everyone
you